So to underscore the conflict of interest, I'm
going to share a very quick case study.
And by the way, the resources of this
session are available along with this video.
So the case facts are those.
Grenda PLC, manufacturers of baby cereal, recently recalled
a batch of contaminated cereal that had reportedly
caused significant harm, including hearing and visual impairment
to many babies.
A class action has been instituted and the
board has convened an emergency meeting to decide
next steps.
A decision needs to be taken regarding legal
representation.
Across the country, there are two top law
firms with the expertise in this area of
the law, Clarkson LLP and Lakeshore LLP.
Clarkson has been retained by the plaintiffs.
The principal partner of Lakeshore is married to
the CEO of Grenda PLC.
What are the issues here?
The issues here are essentially around conflict of
interest.
The CEO of Grenda PLC, the manufacturers of
the contaminated baby product, is married to the
principal partner in the law firm of Clarkson
LLP.
This already suggests that there's a conflict of
interest.
In determining whether or not to proceed with
Clarkson LLP, the major consideration of the board
would be what is the best interest of
the company.
However, there are certain steps that are required
to be taken by the CEO of Grenda
PLC.
The first is disclosure of the conflict.
She has to disclose to the board that
her spouse is the principal partner at Clarkson
LLP.
After the disclosure, she has to recuse herself
and this means actually leaving the meeting.
If it's a virtual meeting, she needs to
exit the meeting.
If it's an in-person meeting, she needs
to also physically exit the meeting.
The remaining members of the board then have
to take a decision as to whether or
not the conflict of interest is material, whether
or not they want to go ahead with
hiring the law firm that is a related
party.
The major consideration, like I said, is what
is in the best interest of the business.
The best interest of the business at this
point is to hire the top rated law
firm that will be able to hold its
own against the Lakeshore that has been hired
by the plaintiffs.
And so the board will consider the best
interest of the company and take a decision
to hire that top rated law firm regardless
of the conflict of interest.
However, in communicating the information to the CEO
and in entering into the agreement with her
spouse, the CEO will have to refuse from
the engagement itself.
She's not going to be involved in the
negotiation of the fees.
feedback from the client, from the solicitors firm,
just so that there's that separation.
And like I said, she'll be ring-fenced.
The board might even decide to set up
a board committee that would pursue the engagement
and, like I said, ring-fence the CEO.
So the steps, just to go over the
steps again, the conflict would be identified by
the director that is conflicted, whether it's a
potential conflict or one that is likely to
crystallise or one that has already manifested.
If a director is also aware that a
colleague on the board has a conflict of
interest, they also have a responsibility to disclose
that conflict.
So the disclosure is accepting the, identifying the
conflict is the first step.
The next step is disclosure.
The third step is recusal.
Recusal means exiting the meeting, not being part
of the conversation, and leaving the remaining directors
to take a decision.
And like I said, what is underlying the
decision they want to take is what is
in the best interest of the organisation.
The director that is conflicted is then invited
back into the room, and the board's decision
is communicated to them.
In communicating the decision to the director, there's
no need to go into the conversation that
had taken place because the whole essence of
having them excuse themselves in the first place
is to give the board an opportunity of
discussion without their influence or their contribution.